Guide to the Kenneth W. Faig, Jr. archive on Robert H. Barlow 1876-1973 (bulk 1932-1973)
Brown University Library
Kenneth W. Faig, Jr. archive on Robert H. Barlow
Faig (Kenneth W. Jr.) archive on Robert H. Barlow
1876-1973
(bulk 1932-1973)
Ms.2018.019
John Hay Library University Archives and Manuscripts Box A Brown University Providence, RI, 02912 Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148 Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu
0.5 linear feet
Faig, Kenneth W.
The materials in this collection were compiled by Kenneth W. Faig, Jr. during 1970-1975 while conducting research for a biography of Robert H. Barlow. The materials include: microfilm of Barlow's literary and scholarly papers made by Barlow's friend George T. Smisor; copies of letters to his brother Wayne Everett Barlow and other family members; photographs of Barlow as a child and his homes; research correspondence with George T. Smisor, E. Hoffman Price, Thomas Hart Benton, and Roy A. Squires.
Biographical/Historical Note
Kenneth W. Faig, Jr. has been researching all aspects of the life and work of weird fiction writer Howard P. Lovecraft, including the lives of his family and associates, for most of his career. Faig's research included the life of Robert H. Barlow who was appointed by Lovecraft as the executor of his literary estate. Faig began compiling information about Barlow during graduate school at Brown University. He graduated from Northwestern University in 1970 and was enrolled as a masters degree student at Brown University from 1970-1972.
Collection information
The materials in this collection were compiled by Kenneth W. Faig, Jr. during 1970-1975 while conducting research for a biography of Robert H. Barlow. The materials include: microfilm of Barlow's literary and scholarly papers made by Barlow's friend George T. Smisor; copies of letters to his brother Wayne Everett Barlow and other family members; photographs of Barlow as a child and his homes; research correspondence with George T. Smisor, E. Hoffman Price, Thomas Hart Benton, and Roy A. Squires.
There are no restrictions on access, except that the collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.
This collection is arranged in 3 series.
Series 1. Primary Materials
Series 2. Secondary Materials
Series 3. Research correspondence with Kenneth W. Faig
Administrative information
Gift of Kenneth W. Faig in 1991.
These materials were compiled by Kenneth W. Faig Jr. during 1970-1975. Faig deposited the collection with the Netzahaulcoyotl Historical Society in Oakland, California in 1975. Faig decided to make a permanent donation of the materials to Brown University in 1988. The materials arrived at Brown University in 1991.
Names
Barlow, R. H. (Robert Hayward), 1918-1951; Lovecraft, H. P. (Howard Phillips), 1890-1937--Friends and associates; Smisor, George T.; Benton, Thomas Hart, 1889-1975; Price, E. Hoffmann; Squires, Roy A.
Subjects
Authors, American--20th century--Biography; Poets, American--20th century--Biography
- Primary Materials, Series 1
  - Robert Hayward Barlow Microfilm: Reel 1, 1951 (Box 2, Reel 1)
    Microfilm of the personal and literary papers of Robert Hayward Barlow (RHB), photographed by George T. Smisor (GTS) In 1951. Three 100-foot reels. (The original reels 3 and 4, each 50 feet, were spliced to make the current reel 3/4.)
  - Robert Hayward Barlow Microfilm: Reel 2, 1951 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Robert Hayward Barlow Microfilm: Reel 3, 1951 (Box 2, Reel 3)
    Pre-Activist poems, published stories and poems, miscellaneous items dealing with his work in art and anthropology 1938-1950
  - Robert Hayward Barlow Microfilm: Reel 4, 1951 (Box 2, Reel 4)
    George Tupper Letters to RHB; H.P. Lovecraft Letters to RHB
  - House of Tlaloc (1), 1951 (Box 2, Reel 5)
    Microfilm of House of Tlaloc correspondence, photographed by George T. Smisor In 1951. Two reels.
  - House of Tlaloc (2), 1951 (Box 2, Reel 6)
  - Weird Tales - Volume 1, No.1-4, 1951 (Box 2, Reel 7)
    Microfilm of the science fiction journal "Weird Tales", Volume 1, No. 1,2,3,4 dated March, April, May and June of 1923. Microfilmed by George T. Smisor at the Biblioteca Benjamin Franklin, Paseo de la Reforma #34, Mexico in 1951. Sent to David A. Jonah, Brown University Librarian, March 16, 1951.
  - Barlow Family Material Relating to RHB, 1933-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Sarah Barlow, compiler, Collection of Barlow family material relating to RHB. Correspondence of RHB to his mother, his father, and his brother. Transcription of RHB's 1933 diary and his mother's Mexican travelogue. Newspaper cuttings pertaining to RHB and his family. Genealogical notes by RHB and sundry writings. Mostly xerox copies of originals; a few carbon copies of typed transcriptions, slightly edited. Organized and annotated by Sarah Barlow.
  - Collection of photographs assembled by George Smisor, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Collection of photographs made and annotated by George T. Smisor. Two large photographs of RHB. Six smaller photographs: two of Barlow's home, three of his grave site, and one of George T. Smisor.
  - Collection of photographs assembled by Sarah Barlow, 1876-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Collection of photographs compiled and annotated by Sarah (Mrs. Everett Wayne) Barlow. Photographs of RHB, his family, and his homes.
  - RHB, correspondence with Claire Beck, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    RHB, correspondence with Claire Beck (The Futile Press). Xerox of typed transcription by Beck.
  - RHB, correspondence with Larry Farsaci, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence with Larry Farsaci. Xerox copies prepared by Larry Farsaci.
  - RHB, Letter to Robert Ervin Howard, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    RHB, letter to Robert Ervin Howard, July 5, 1936. Xerox copy prepared by Glenn Lord, agent for the Howard Estate.
  - George T. Smisor correspondence relating to Barlow Estate, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    George T. Smisor, compiler, et alii, Collection of correspondence relating to the disposition of Barlow's estate.
  - Bernice L. Barlow, T.L.S. to Hoffman Price, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Benace L. Barlow, T.L.S. to E. Hoffmann Price, dated May 20, 1951. Original letter, donated by Price.
  - H.P. Lovecraft: Sketch of Barlow Home, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Howard Phillips Lovecraft (HPL), sketch of Barlow home in Cassia. Prom a letter to Dwayne W. Rimel, 1934 or 1935, in the John Hay Library, Brown University. Not to be reproduced w/o permission of Brown University.
  - RHB-H.P. Lovecraft "Bouts Rimes", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Howard P. Lovecraft and RHB, "Bouts Rimes". Typed transcription or T.Ms. In the John Hay Library, Brown University. Reference to Barlow's memoir of Lovecraft in Marginalia.
- Secondary Materials, Series 2
  - J. Vernon Shea "R.H. Barlow: Lost Little Boy", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    J. Vernon Shea, "R. H. Barlow: Lost Little Boy". A sketch intended for Shea's work—in—progress, The Lovecraft Circle. Not to be reproduced or quoted without permission of J. Vernon Shea, 10621 Governor Avenue, Cleveland, Ohio 44111
  - Ignacio Bernal: Obituary of RHB, BBAA 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Ignacio Bernal, "Robert H. Barlow", from the Boletin Bibliografico de Antropologia Americana (BBAA), vol. 13 pt. 1, 1950, pp. 301-304. Xerox copy.
  - RHB, Bibliography from Boletin Bibliographico de Atropologia Americana (BBAA), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Bibliographies of Barlow's scholarly articles. From BBAA (v. 10, 1947, pp. 278-282), covering the years, 1942-1947, and the same source (v. 13, pt. 2, 1950, pp. 249-251), covering the years 1947-1951. Xerox copies. (N.B.: The Smisor microfilm contains a fine bibliography of Barlow's literary work, both professional and amateur.)
  - H.P. Lovecraft Notes on Correspondence with Richard Ely Morse, 1932-1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Howard P. Lovecraft, correspondence to Richard Ely Morse, 1932-937. Notes and transcriptions by Kenneth W. Faig, Jr. (KWF). From the letter file in the New York Public Library.
  - RHB Poems for a Competition, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    RHB, Poems for a Competition, 1942. Xerox copy.
  - RHB View from a Hill, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    RHB, View from a Hill, 1947. Xerox copy.
  - RHB, "Annals of the Jinns", 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    RHB, "Annals of the Jinns". Published as a serial in The Fantasy Fan. Xerox copies.
  - RHB, correspondence resumes and notes on correspondence. with A.E. Gamwell and John Hay Library, 1935-1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Kenneth W. Faig, compiler, resumes of correspondence of RHB with Annie E. P. Gamwell and the John Hay Library. From the copies in the John Hay Library, Brown University.
  - RHB, Untitled poem Couleur de Rose, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Benton E. Wetzel, publisher, Couleur de Rose, number 4, Christmas, 1938. Amateur magazine with an untitled poem by RHB. Xerox copy.
  - George Smisor, collection of title pages of works by RHB, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    George T. Smisor, compiler, Collection of title pages of scholarly works by RHB. Xerox copies.
  - Kenneth Faig misc. research notes and letters on RHB, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Kenneth W. Faig, compiler, miscellaneous research notes and letters pertaining to RHB.
  - Roy A. Squires Catalog II, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Roy A. Squires, compiler, Clark Ashton Smith, H. P. Lovecraft, Robert H. Barlow: Catalog II, Glendale, California, n.d. /1969/.
  - Mooser, "A Study of Robert Barlow", Mexico Quarterly Review 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Clare Mooser, "A Study of Robert Barlow: The T. E. Lawrence of Mexico", Mexico Quarterly Review, v. 3 no. 2 1968, pp. 5-12.
- Research correspondence with Kenneth W. Faig, Series 3
  - Barlow, Everett Wayne and Sarah Barlow, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Everett Wayne Barlow and Sarah Barlow
  - Barrett, Dr. C. L. (M.D.), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Beck, Claire, 1937-1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    See also Box 1 Folder 4.
  - Benton, Thomas Hart, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Blish, James, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bradofsky, Hyman, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Brown, Rosalie Moore, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes xerox copies of an article on RHB from Number, a letter of RHB to Mrs. Brown, and RHB's design for a Brown family coat of arms.
  - Coslet, Walter A., 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Derleth, August W., 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Farsaci, Larry B., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    See also Box 1 Folder 5.
  - Hart, Lawrence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Draft and final letter by Kenneth W. Faig only. No reply received.
  - Kirk, Barbara A., 1941-1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    With photographs of jewelry designed by RHB, transcript of RHB's college record, and xerox copy of postcard from RHB.
  - Everts, R. Alain (aka R. Alan Kirsch), 1944-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Selection of correspondence with Kenneth W. Faig pertaining to RHB. With small photograph of RHB from Everts collection.
  - Barlow, Robert H. "The Extent of the Empire of the Culhua Mexica", 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Book by Barlow ("Ibero-Americana:28")
  - Langworthy, Dorcas, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    No reply received.
  - La Rue, Carolyn, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Price, Edgar Hoffman, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Smisor, George T., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    See also Box 1 Folders 2 and 20, Box 2 Reels 1-6.
  - Squires, Roy A., 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Selection of correspondence with Kenneth W. Faig pertaining to RHB.
  - Sterling, Dr. Kenneth (M.D.), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Warner, Harry Jr., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Wesson, Sheldon, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Wollheim, Donald, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)